What I want to talk about today is one idea.
الفكرة التي اريد ان اتحدث عنها اليوم
It's an idea for a new kind of school,
هي عبارة عن نوع جديد من المدارس
which turns on its head much of our conventional thinking
و التي ستغير كثيرا من تفكيرنا التقليدي
about what schools are for and how they work.
حول الهدف من المدارس و كيفية عملها
And it might just be coming to a neighborhood near you soon.
و قد تفتح احداها قريبا في الحي الذي تسكن فيه.
Where it comes from
ومصدر تلك المدارس هي
is an organization called the Young Foundation,
منظمة تسمى "مؤسسة الشباب"
which, over many decades,
و التي عبر عدة عقود
has come up with many innovations in education, like the Open University
توصلت الى العديد من الاختراعات في مجال التعليم، مثل الجامعة المفتوحة
and things like Extended Schools,
و اشياء اخرى كالمدارس المطورة،
Schools for Social Entrepreneurs, Summer Universities
مدارس رجال الاعمال الاجتماعيين، الجامعات الصيفية
and the School of Everything.
و مدارس كل شئ
And about five years ago, we asked
قبل ٥ اعوام تساءلنا
what was the most important need for innovation
ما هي اهم الاشياء التي تحتاج الى الاختراع
in schooling here in the U.K.
في مجال التدريس هنا في المملكة المتحدة
And we felt the most important priority
و شعرنا ان الاولوية القصوى
was to bring together two sets of problems.
هي بان نجمع معا نوعين من المشاكل
One was large numbers of bored teenagers
الاولى تتمثل في عدد الكبير من المراهقين الذين يشعرون بملل
who just didn't like school,
و الذين ببساطة لا يحبون المدرسة،
couldn't see any relationship between what they learned in school
و لم نجد اي علاقة بين ما تعلموه في المدارس
and future jobs.
و بين اعمالهم المستقبلية.
And employers who kept complaining
و الثانية في ارباب العمل الذين ظلوا يشكون
that the kids coming out of school weren't actually ready for real work,
بان الطلاب المتخرجين من المدارس لم يكونوا مهيئين للعمل الجاد،
didn't have the right attitudes and experience.
و لم يكن لديهم السلوك و الخبره اللازمين.
And so we try to ask:
لذلك نحاول ان نسال
What kind of school would have the teenagers fighting to get in,
ما نوع المدارس التي ستصارع من اجل ابقاء المراهقين،
not fighting to stay out?
و ليس من اجل اخراجهم؟
And after hundreds of conversations
و بعد مئات من المحادثات
with teenagers and teachers and parents
مع المراهقين و المدرسين و الاباء
and employers and schools
و ارباب العمل و المدارس
from Paraguay to Australia,
من برغواي الى استراليا،
and looking at some of the academic research,
و بعد الاطلاع على بعض البحوث الاكاديمية،
which showed the importance
و التي اظهرت مدى اهمية
of what's now called non-cognitive skills --
ما يسمى اليوم ب المهارات غير المعرفية
the skills of motivation, resilience --
(مهارات التحفيز، المرونة)
and that these are as important
تلك المهارات هي بنفس القدر من الاهمية
as the cognitive skills -- formal academic skills --
التي تتمتع بها المهارات المعرفية (المهارات الاكاديمية الرسمية)
we came up with an answer, a very simple answer in a way,
و قد توصلنا الى حل، و هو حل بسيط من ناحية،
which we called the Studio School.
و اطلقنا عليه اسم "المدرسة الاستوديو"
And we called it a studio school
و سميناها بالمدرسة الاستوديو
to go back to the original idea of a studio in the Renaissance
و ذلك بالعودة الى الفكرة الاصلية في عصر النهضة
where work and learning are integrated.
حيث يندمج العمل مع التعليم.
You work by learning,
نعمل من خلال التعليم،
and you learn by working.
و نتعلم من خلال العمل.
And the design we came up with had the following characteristics.
و تتمتع التصميم التي توصلنا اليها بالصفات التالية.
First of all, we wanted small schools --
اولا كان هدفنا المدارس الصغيرة،
about 300, 400 pupils --
من 300 الى 400 تلميذ،
14 to 19 year-olds,
ما بين اعمار 14 الى 19 عام،
and critically, about 80 percent of the curriculum done
80 بالمائة من المنهاج الدراسي تقريبا يتم تدريسها
not through sitting in classrooms,
ليس من خلال الجلوس في الفصول الدراسية
but through real-life, practical projects,
و لكن من خلال الحياة الواقعية، المشاريع التطبيقية،
working on commission
العمل عبر المجموعة
to businesses, NGO's and others.
مع الشركات التجارية، المنظمات غير الحكومية و جهات اخرى.
That every pupil would have a coach, as well as teachers,
و ان يكون لكل تلميذ مدرب و مدرسين ايضا،
who would have timetables
و سيكون لديهم جداول زمنية
much more like a work environment in a business.
تشبه في ذلك الى حد بعيد بيئة العمل الخاصة التي تسود في الشركات.
And all of this will be done within the public system,
و كل ذلك سيتم عمله في اطار النظام التعليمي العام،
funded by public money,
و يتم تمويله من الموازنة العامة،
but independently run.
لكنه يدار بشكل مستقل.
And all at no extra cost, no selection,
و كل ذلك من دون اي تكاليف اضافية، او اختيار،
and allowing the pupils the route into university,
و اتاحة المجال امام التلاميذ للالتحاق بالجامعة،
even if many of them would want to become entrepreneurs
حتى وان اراد العديد منهم ان يصبحوا أصحاب اعمال
and have manual jobs as well.
فيكون لديهم مهن يدوية ايضا.
Underlying it was some very simple ideas
خلفها كان عبارة عن افكار بسيطة جدا
that large numbers of teenagers learn best by doing things,
ان معظم المراهقين يتعلمون الاشياء بشكل افضل من خلال التطبيق العملي
they learn best in teams
و يتعلمون بشكل افضل كفريق
and they learn best by doing things for real --
و يتعلمون بشكل افضل من خلال التطبيق العملي
all the opposite of what mainstream schooling
بعكس غالبية المدارس
actually does.
و طريقة عملها.
Now that was a nice idea,
و الان فقد كانت تلك فكرة جيدة،
so we moved into the rapid prototyping phase.
و انتقلنا الى مرحلة النموذج السريع.
We tried it out,
و قمنا بتجربته،
first in Luton --
في البداية في لوتن،
famous for its airport and not much else, I fear --
المعروفة بمطارها و ليس هناك شئ اخر، اني اخشى ...
and in Blackpool -- famous for its beaches and leisure.
و في بلاك بول المشهورة بشواطئها و بالسياحة
And what we found -- and we got quite a lot of things wrong
ماذا وجدنا هناك ؟ كثير من الاشياء الخاطئة
and then improved them --
و قد قمنا بتصحيحها ...
but we found that the young people loved it.
و لكننا وجدنا ان الشباب كانوا يحبونها
They found it much more motivational, much more exciting
و قد وجودوها محفزة و مشوقة
than traditional education.
اكثر من التعليم التقليدي.
And perhaps most important of all,
و ربما الاهم من ذلك كله،
two years later when the exam results came through,
انه بعد مضي عامين عندما صدرت نتائج الامتحانات،
the pupils who had been put on these field trials
الطلاب الذين شملتهم تلك التجارب الميدانية
who were in the lowest performing groups
و الذين كانوا في اسفل القائمة من حيث الاداء
had jumped right to the top --
قد قفزوا الى الصدارة ...
in fact, pretty much at the top decile of performance
في الواقع الى اوائل قائمة المتصدرين من حيث الاداء
in terms of GCSE's,
من حيث شهادات الثانوية العامة
which is the British marking system.
و هو نظام التقييم البريطاني.
Now not surprisingly,
لا عجب
that influenced some people to think we were onto something.
ققد اثر ذلك على بعض الناس ان يظنوا باننا نجهز لشئ ما.
The minister of education
وزير التعليم
down south in London
و هو في لندن جنوبا
described himself as a "big fan."
وصفه نفسه بانه "من كبار المعجبين"
And the business organizations thought we were onto something
كما ان منظمات الاعمال اعتقدت باننا كنا نجهز لشئ ما
in terms of a way of preparing children much better
فيما يخص طريقة اعدادنا للاطفال بشكل افضل
for real-life work today.
لمواجهة الحياة الواقعية التي نعيشها اليوم.
And indeed, the head of the Chambers of Commerce
و فعلا فان رئيس الغرف التجارية
is now the chairman of the Studio Schools Trust
قد اصبح اليوم رئيسا لمجلس ادارة اتحاد المدارس الاستوديو
and helping it, not just with big businesses,
و لا تقتصر مساعدته على الاعمال الكبيرة فحسب
but small businesses all over the country.
و لكنها ايضا تشمل الاعمال الصغيرة في عموم البلاد.
We started with two schools.
بدأنا بمدرستين.
That's grown this year to about 10.
و أرتفع هذا العدد الى 10.
And next year, we're expecting about 35 schools
و نتوقع ان يرتفع العدد الى 35 مدرسة في العام القادم
open across England,
في عموم انحاء انجلترا،
and another 40 areas
و هناك 40 منطقة اخرى
want to have their own schools opening --
ترغب في افتتاح مدارس خاصة بهم
a pretty rapid spread
و يعد ذلك انتشار سريع
of this idea.
لهذه الفكرة.
Interestingly,
من المدهش
it's happened almost entirely without media coverage.
ان كل ذلك حدث بدون تغطية اعلامية تقريبا.
It's happened almost entirely without big money behind it.
حدث كل ذلك دون ان تكون هناك تكاليف كبيرة خلف هذا العمل.
It spread almost entirely through word of mouth, virally,
و انتشرت الفكرة بشكل كلي تقريبا من خلال انتقال الكلام بين الناس، كالعدوى
across teachers, parents,
بين المدرسين، الاباء،
people involved in education.
و الناس المنتمين الى قطاع التعليم.
And it spread because of the power of an idea --
و انتشرت بسبب قوة الفكرة...
so the very, very simple idea
فالفكرة البسيطة جدا جدا
about turning education on its head
عن قلب النظام التعليمي على راسه
and putting the things which were marginal,
و وضع الاشياء التي كانت جانبية،
things like working in teams, doing practical projects,
كالعمل في مجموعات، القيام بمشاريع تطبيقية،
and putting them right at the heart of learning,
ووضعها في صميم النظام التعليمي،
rather than on the edges.
بدلا من الجوانب.
Now there's a whole set of new schools
يوجد اليوم نوع مختلف تماما من المدارس الجديدة
opening up this autumn.
و التي ستفتح ابوابها هذا الخريف
This is one from Yorkshire
هذه مدرسة في يورك شير
where, in fact, my nephew, I hope, will be able to attend it.
و التي في الحقيقة سيدرس بها ابن اخي
And this one is focused
و هي تركز
on creative and media industries.
على صناعتي الاعلام و الابداع.
Other ones have a focus on health care,
و بعضها تركز على الرعاية الصحية،
tourism, engineering
السياحة، الهندسة
and other fields.
و بعض المجالات الاخرى.
We think we're onto something.
نعتقد باننا بصدد عمل شئ ما
It's not perfect yet,
و لم يصل حد الكمال بعد
but we think this is one idea
و لكن نعتقد ان تلك الفكرة
which can transform the lives
يمكن ان تغير من حياة
of thousands, possibly millions, of teenagers
الالاف، بل ربما الملايين من المراهقين
who are really bored by schooling.
الذين فعلا ضجروا من الدراسة التقليدية.
It doesn't animate them.
فهي لا تحفزهم.
They're not like all of you who can sit in rows
انهم ليسوا مثلكم. فهم لا يجلسون في صفوف
and hear things said to you for hour after hour.
و لا يستمعون لاشياء تلقى عليهم ساعة تلو الاخرى
They want to do things, they want to get their hands dirty,
يريدون ان يقومون بعمل اشياء، يريدون ان تتسخ اياديهم،
they want education to be for real.
يريدون ان يكون التعليم واقعي
And my hope is that some of you out there
املي ان يستطيع بعض منكم
may be able to help us.
العمل على مساعدتنا.
We feel we're on the beginning of a journey
نشعر باننا في بداية رحلة
of experiment and improvement
من التجارب و التطوير
to turn the Studio School idea
لتحويل فكرة المدرسة الاستوديو
into something which is present,
الى شئ من الحاضر،
not as a universal answer for every child,
و ليست كخيار عالمي لجميع الاطفال
but at least as an answer for some children in every part of the world.
و لكن على الاقل كخيار لبعض الاطفال في جميع انحاء العالم
And I hope that a few of you at least can help us make that happen.
امل ان يستطيع البعض منكم على الاقل مساعدتنا في تحقيق ذلك
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)